<!-- BEGIN: LOGIN -->
<chapter id="login">
	<title>Logging In</title>
	<para>
		After <application>Gabber</application> is loaded, the first
		thing to do is connect and log in to a Jabber server. <xref linkend="figure-login"/>
		shows the default <interface>Login</interface> dialog where
		information about a user account can be entered. 
		<screenshot id="figure-login">
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="login.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>A screenshot of the login dialog.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>Login</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</screenshot>
	</para>
	<para>
		After entering user information into the required <guilabel>Username</guilabel>,
		<guilabel>Server</guilabel> and <guilabel>Password</guilabel> fields, click
		<guibutton>Login</guibutton> to connect and authenticate to the <link
		linkend="login-server-def">server</link>. The <guilabel>Resource</guilabel> field is
		required (<link linkend="login-resource-def">see below</link>). Unless some unique circumstances
		are involved, the <guilabel>Port</guilabel> field should equal 5222, Jabber's default port.
		The priority option is not required to be changed unless desired (<link linkend="login-priority-def">see
		the definition below</link>).
	</para>
	<para>
		All of the information on the <interface>Login</interface> dialog can be edited from the <interface>Connection
		Settings</interface> dialog, accessible from the <guimenu>Gabber</guimenu> menu.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry id="login-server-def">
			<term>Server</term>
			<listitem><para>
				As Jabber is a distributed architecture like the Internet's email
				system, the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> field is required.
				If no other Jabber server is available, the jabber.com server is currently
				available for public, stable use.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry id="login-resource-def">
			<term>Resource</term>
			<listitem><para>
				A <wordasword>Resource</wordasword> in Jabber is used to
				differentiate between different account connections. It can be any value such as
				"Gabber" or "Home" as long as it is unique for the account. By having unique
				Resources, a user can login to the same server using the same Jabber account
				numerous times.
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry id="login-priority-def">
			<term>Priority</term>
			<listitem><para>
				Using priorities, another client can be connected to take lower or higher priority than
				existing clients. For instance, if <application>Gabber</application> is connected at
				priority 0 and another <application>Gabber</application> session is initiated at
				priority 1, the client with priority 0 will receive incoming messages (unless the
				message is bound specifically to the lower priority client).
			</para></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</chapter>
<!-- END: LOGIN -->
