<!-- BEGIN: MSG -->
	<chapter id="msg">
		<title>Messaging and Chatting</title>
		<para>
			Since the first instant messaging client, there have been numerous ways to send and receive messages
			with other users. Two distinct interfaces have been developed for one-on-one communication, and nearly
			all commercial and open source clients now adhere to these two <quote>standards.</quote> For group communication,
			a style similar to GUI IRC chat has developed.
		</para>
		<sect1 id="msg-encrypt">
			<title>Encrypted Messages</title>
			<para>
				Through the use of <ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnupg.org">GnuPG</ulink>, a free software replacement
				for PGP, <application>Gabber</application> can send and receive encrypted messages with other Jabber clients capable of message
				encryption. Before being able to use encryption, GnuPG must already be configured and a public key must
				already be sent to a public key repository. Refer to GnuPG's <ulink type="http"
				url="http://www.gnupg.org">web site</ulink> for complete information about this process.
			</para>
			<para>
				To start using encryption, it must be enabled on the <interface>Encryption</interface> tab in the <link
				linkend="pref">Preferences dialog</link>. After selecting a secret key to use, apply the changes and close
				the dialog. The passphrase will then be requested for the key. After receiving the correct passphrase,
				<application>Gabber</application> will notify users on the roster that encrypted messages can be sent 
				and received.
			</para>
			<para>
				The option to send encrypted messages is given on each message dialog. If an incoming message or conversation
				is encrypted, a locked padlock will be shown. Otherwise, an unlocked padlock will be shown in the dialog.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="msg-que">
			<title>Message Queueing</title>
			<para>
				By default all messages are queued in <application>Gabber</application>'s spool. This means that
				the message will not automatically show on screen but will instead wait to be opened. If
				<application>Gabber</application> is closed before messages are viewed, it will store them
				until the next time <application>Gabber</application> is run. When a new message is received from
				a user on the roster, the user's name will flash with an alternate color and the status icon
				will change to a flashing message. To access the message, just double click the user. If the group
				the user is in is not expanded, the group name will flash. In addition to roster visual notifications,
				the GNOME status docklet icon will indicate a new message. Double click the icon and the new message
				will be viewable.
			</para>
			<para>
				Customization of queueing behavior is available from the Messages <link linkend="pref">Preferences</link>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="msg-normal">
			<title>Normal Messages</title>
			<para>
				The most common format is modeled after Mirabilis ICQ's send and receive dialogs. This format is similar
				to email messages in that the entire conversation is not contained (or shown) within a window, but only
				the current message.
			</para>
			<sect2 id="msg-normal-send">
				<title>Sending a New Message</title>
				<para>
					To send a normal message to a user in <application>Gabber</application>, right click on
					a user in the <link linkend="users">roster</link> and select <guimenuitem>Message</guimenuitem>. A <interface>Send
					Message</interface> dialog appears (shown in <xref linkend="figure-msg-normal-send"/>) for the user to type a message.

					<screenshot id="figure-msg-normal-send">
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="msg-normal.png" format="PNG"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>A screenshot of a normal message dialog.</phrase>
							</textobject>
							<caption>
								<para>Send Message</para>
							</caption>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="msg-normal-reply">
				<title>Responding to Messages</title>
				<para>
					When a normal message is received, a new window will be created to contain the received message
					and a text entry box for the user to input a response. If more messages are received from the same
					person, the <guibutton>Read Next</guibutton> button will become active to allow the user to view the next
					received message. To turn display of received messages off, simply toggle the <guibutton>Received Message</guibutton>
					button on the message toolbar. After typing a message into the <guilabel>Reply to:</guilabel> entry box, simply click
					<guibutton>Send</guibutton> to send the message. If the <guibutton>Don't close this dialog</guibutton> button on the toolbar
					is toggled, the message will be sent and the message entry dialog box will be cleared for a new message. If the option is not
					toggled, the dialog will then close and any unviewed messages will be lost.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="msg-normal-options">
				<title>Options</title>
				<para>
					<application>Gabber</application> provides several options when sending a normal message. These
					options are available via the simple toolbar at the top of each normal message. The following options
					are available (some options are only available when responding to a message):
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Quote Received Message in Reply - Copies the received message into the send message text box for editing.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Send as One-on-One Chat - Specifies that upon receiving a response from the receiver,
							<application>Gabber</application> should load the rest of the conversation in a <link linkend="msg-ooo">One-on-One chat</link>.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Encrypt this message - If <link linkend="msg-encrypt">encryption</link> is configured and enabled properly,
							this option will be available to allow the message to be encrypted. If the recipient does not have
							a public key, <application>Gabber</application> will respond with an error and ask if it is acceptable
							to send the message without encryption.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Show/Hide Advanced Options - Toggles viewing of more advanced options.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Don't close this dialog - After sending the current message, <application>Gabber</application>
							will clear the text and allow for a new message to be entered from the same dialog.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Show/Hide Received Message - Toggles viewing of received message.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Add this User to Roster - Loads the <link linkend="users-adduser">Add User</link> dialog to
							add the current user to the roster.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							View Contact Info - Loads the <link linkend="users-edituser">Contact Information</link>
							and queries the server for this user's information.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Message History - Loads the history dialog with the complete message history of this user.
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="msg-ooo">
			<title>One-on-One Chats</title>
			<para>
				Another popular format for sending and receiving messages is styled after America Online's Instant
				Messenger. One window is loaded with the entire conversation contained in the window. The window
				contains one main area for the conversation, different options for sending a message may be shown
				and a small input line for entering the messages is at the bottom of the window.
				Each message is prepended with the author's user name in brackets (&lt;&gt;).
			</para>
			<para>
				To start a one-one-one chat with a user in the <link linkend="users">roster</link>, right click on
				their name and select <guimenuitem>One-on-One Chat</guimenuitem>. Once the <interface>One-on-One</interface>
				window is loaded, simply type a message in the lower entry box and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
				Messages that the user sends will be prepended with the user name and
				messages from the other user will be prepended with their nickname.
				<screenshot id="figure-msg-ooo">
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="msg-ooo.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>A screenshot of a one-on-one chat window.</phrase>
						</textobject>
						<caption>
							<para>One-on-One Chat</para>
						</caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</para>
			<sect2 id="msg-ooo-info">
				<title>Information Indicators</title>
				<para>
					Below the toolbar is a line of text and graphical
					information pertinent to the user and conversation. To 
					find out more information about each icon, hover over
					the icon for a few second.
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>Current status - The availability status
						of the user is displayed to the left of the user's
						name.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>User name - The user's name and resource
						is displayed next to the Current Status
						indicator.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Music information - If the user is
						using a Jabber client that supports the music
						information, a music indicator will appear to the right
						side of the user's name. By hovering over the icon
						with the mouse, information about the song the user
						is listening to will be displayed.
						<application>Gabber</application> will send this
						information to other users if the option is enabled at
						compile time.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Encryption information - The status
						of encryption for this chat will be shown to the far
						right. If the padlock is unlocked, the messages are not
						being encrypted.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="msg-ooo-options">
				<title>Options</title>
				<para>
					Like normal messages, one-on-one chats have several options available from a toolbar along the 
					top of the chat window. The following options are available:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Send as Normal Message - If enabled, messages sent to the user are sent as <link
							linkend="msg-normal">normal messages</link>. This is useful, for instance, to 
							gain the receiver's attention since the message will probably appear in front
							of any other windows that are open on their desktop.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Encrypt this message - Similarly to normal message encryption, if <link linkend="msg-encrypt">encryption</link>
							is configured and enabled properly, this option will be available to allow the conversation to be encrypted.
							If the recipient does not have a public key, <application>Gabber</application> will respond with an error
							and ask if it is acceptable to send the message without encryption.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Add this User to Roster - Loads the <link linkend="users-adduser">Add User</link> dialog to
							add the current user to the roster.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							View Contact Info - Loads the <link linkend="users-edituser">Contact Info</link> dialog
							and queries the server for this user's information.
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							Message History - Loads the history dialog to view the entire history of messages
							with this user.
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="msg-gc">
			<title>Group Chats</title>
			<para>Group chats allow any number of people to connect with each
			other and discuss various topics. Similar interfaces are available
			in other instant messaging systems and the famous IRC service.</para>
			<sect2 id="msg-gc-join">
				<title>Joining a Group Chat</title>
				<para>
					Upon initiating <guimenuitem>Group Chat</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>Services</guimenu> menu,
					the <interface>Join Group Chat</interface> dialog
					will load for the user to fill in the required group chat information. After filling in the
					desired information, click <guibutton>Join Room</guibutton> to join the discussion.
				</para>
				<sect3 id="msg-gc-join-jabber">
					<title>Jabber Group Chat</title>
					<para>
						To join a Jabber group chat the room and the group chat server. Jabber.org runs a
						public group chat server at conference.jabber.org. The protocol should be set to
						"Jabber Group Chat".
					</para>
					<note id="msg-gc-join-jabber-backlog">
						<title>Jabber Group Chat Backlog</title>
						<para>
							The Jabber group chat server will send the last 20 messages that were sent in
							the room to any users joining. This is a highly useful feature that allows new
							joiners to see what is being discussed instead of just being thrown right into
							the conversation.
						</para>
					</note>
				</sect3>
				<sect3 id="msg-gc-join-irc">
					<title>IRC</title>
					<para>
						To join an Internet Relay Chat (IRC) channel, set the server to "irc.jabber.org",
						change the protocol to "IRC" and set the IRC server to whichever IRC server is desired.
						The channel name must be prefixed with an ampersand (&amp;) or a hash (#).
					</para>
					<para>
						As an example, to join the main GNOME IRC channel with <application>Gabber</application>,
						enter "#gnome" for the room, enter "irc.jabber.org" for
						the server, change the protocol to "IRC" and input "irc.gimp.net" in the IRC server field.
					</para>
				</sect3>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="msg-gc-main">
				<title>The Main Attraction</title>
				<para>
					After logging into group chat, the main <interface>Group Chat</interface> window is shown.
					Along the top is the <link linkend="msg-gc-main-toolbar">toolbar</link> with various commands to manipulate the group
					chat. In the center of the window, there are two text areas. The left text box is the main chat
					area where all the messages are passed back and forth among the chat members. To the right of that
					area is the list of current participants in the chat and their current status. To change the 
					status of the user in the group chat session, simply select the desired state from the drop down box
					beneath the list of group chat participants. On the bottom left is an input text box where the user
					can type messages. After pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap>, the message will be
					sent to all the participants and will appear in the main chat box. 
				</para>
				<sect3 id="msg-gc-main-toolbar">
					<title>Group Chat Toolbar</title>
					<para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>
								Invite Contacts - Loads a dialog to allow contacts to be invited to the
								discussion.
							</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								Show/Hide Users in Group - Allows the side panel of group chat participants to be
								toggled on and off.
							</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>
								Message History - Loads the history dialog to view the entire history of messages
								with this group.
							</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>					
					</para>
				</sect3>
				<sect3 id="msg-gc-main-subject">
					<title>Subject</title>
					<para>
						To change the subject (or topic) of the current group, type or edit the subject
						in the <guilabel>Subject:</guilabel> text box and press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key.
					</para>
				</sect3>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="msg-rules">
			<title>Jabber Message Rules</title>
			<para>
				Unique to Jabber is the ability to setup message rules. Message rules allow incoming messages
				to be handled differently based upon criteria such as current presence status; message type;
				incoming message type, subject, sender or receiver. The current interface in
				<application>Gabber</application> for message rule editing is designed for quick editing and
				is not the final interface for rule editing. To access the <interface>Jabber Message Rules
				List</interface> dialog, select <guimenuitem>Jabber Message Rules...</guimenuitem> from the
				<guimenu>Services</guimenu> menu.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <interface>Jabber Message Rules List</interface> dialog is largely self-explanatory.
				A rule is listed by an arbitrary title in the main list and can be set to a higher or lower
				priority with the <guibutton>Up</guibutton> and <guibutton>Down</guibutton> buttons. A
				rule can be edited or removed with the <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton> and
				<guibutton>Remove</guibutton> buttons. Since the edit rule dialog is the same as the
				add rule dialog, it will not be explained. After all edits to the rules are completed (including
				adding, removing and changing the priority), click the <guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>
				button and then close the dialog.
			</para>
			<para>
				Jabber Message Rules are stored on the server and are processed entirely by the server.
				Because of this, a Jabber client does not need to support Jabber Message Rules to be affected
				by them. Also, some rules will be processed even while the user is not connected to the Jabber
				server.
			</para>
			<sect2 id="msg-rules-add">
				<title>Adding a Jabber Message Rule</title>
				<para>
					To add a new rule, click the <guibutton>Add...</guibutton> button on the <interface>Jabber
					Message Rules List</interface> to bring up the <interface>Add a Jabber Message
					Rule</interface> dialog. First, enter a unique identifying name for the rule in the
					rule name text box. Then add at least one condition for the rule to be enacted upon by
					clicking the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button in the <interface>Condition</interface>
					area. A blank condition will appear to allow editing or removal. Simply set the drop down
					box to the desired condition and if necessary, type a string in the text box next to the
					selection box. For instance, if the rule is "If the message is from..." then the user's
					JID (e.g., user@host) would be typed in the text box.
				</para>
				<para>
					The following is a current list of options for "my status is..." and "the message type
					is..." These are actual pieces of the Jabber protocol and must be entered exactly as shown.
					<variablelist>
						<title>Status Types</title>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>away</term>
							<listitem><para>Away</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>chat</term>
							<listitem><para>Free to chat</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>xa</term>
							<listitem><para>Not Available</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>dnd</term>
							<listitem><para>Busy</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>invisible</term>
							<listitem><para>Invisible</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
					<variablelist>
						<title>Message Types</title>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>normal</term>
							<listitem><para>A "normal" message, see <xref linkend="msg-normal"/>.</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>chat</term>
							<listitem><para>An One-on-One chat message, see <xref linkend="msg-ooo"/>.</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>groupchat</term>
							<listitem><para>A groupchat message, see <xref linkend="msg-gc"/>.</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>headline</term>
							<listitem><para>A headline message. There is not currently an interface in
							<application>Gabber</application> to handle headline messages properly.</para></listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</para>
				<para>
					After selecting at least one condition for the rule to be acted upon (more than one condition
					can be specified), actions can be added. Adding an action works the same way as adding a
					condition. Message types are the same as above and when forwarding a message, a valid
					JID must be entered. Again, multiple actions may be entered.
				</para>
				<para>
					To remove any condition or action, simply click the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button to
					the right of the condition or action.
				</para>
			</sect2>	
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
<!-- END: MSG -->
