<!-- BEGIN: PREF -->
	<chapter id="pref">
		<title>Preferences</title>
		<para>
			The <interface>Preferences</interface> is accessible via the <guimenuitem>Preferences...</guimenuitem>
			option in the <guimenu>Gabber</guimenu> menu. It provides a central location for the user to 
			customize various levels of the way <application>Gabber</application> behaves. Options are available
			to customize logging, the appearance of the roster, the way messages are sent and received by
			default, among others.
		</para>
		<sect1 id="pref-interface">
			<title>Interface</title>
			<para>
				The Interface preferences tab has several options to affect the
				display of the <link linkend="main">main window</link>, as well
				as options to enable spelling and the status docklet.
			</para>
			<sect2 id="pref-interface-mainwindow">
				<title>Main Window</title>
				<para>
					<application>Gabber</application> can keep a memory of the main window size and position
					if desired. Note that some window managers will conflict with this memory and may cause
					the window to not appear exactly in the right position.
				</para>
				<para>
					The other option available here is whether or not <application>Gabber</application>
					should display icons on the roster or not.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="pref-interface-toolbars">
				<title>Toolbars</title>
				<para>
					In addition to being able to manually move the toolbars on the main window around,
					they can also be disabled. For more information about the main toolbar and the 
					status indicator, see <xref linkend="main-toolbar"/> and <xref linkend="main-status-user"/>.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="pref-interface-spelling">
				<title>Spelling</title>
				<para>
					If this option is enabled, <application>Gabber</application> will attempt to spell
					check messages while the message is being composed. If the text turns red, the word
					has been identified to be misspelled. Right click on the word to load a menu with
					possible words to replace the highlighted one.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			<sect2 id="pref-interface-docklet">
				<title>Status Docklet</title>
				<para>
					The <link linkend="panel">status docklet</link> can be added or removed from the GNOME panel
					dock with this option.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="pref-msg">
			<title>Messages and Chats</title>
			<para>
				Sending and receiving of messages can be customized in detail to suit a user's preference. If
				<link linkend="msg-ooo">one-on-one chats</link> are always preferred, simply enable the option
				to send all messages as a one-on-one chat by default and enable receiving all messages as
				one-on-one chats.
			</para>
			<para>
				All incoming messages can be queued, or stored, for viewing. To disable queuing for specific
				types of messages, enable the option to automatically open the appropriate message type.
				Most users will want to automatically open <link linkend="msg-ooo">one-on-one chats</link>.
				See <xref linkend="msg-que"/> for more information about message queuing.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="pref-encryption">
			<title>Encryption</title>
			<para>
				The <interface>Encryption</interface> preferences dialog has a few very simple options to enable <link
				linkend="msg-encrypt">message encryption</link>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="pref-autoaway">
			<title>Auto-away</title>
			<para>
				<application>Gabber</application> can automatically change the current <link
				linkend="main-status-user">status</link> in case the user forgets to change the status
				before leaving. After a specified time, <application>Gabber</application> will 
				change the status message to the one specified on this dialog as well as set the status
				to away. After being Away for a specified time, the user will be put into Extended Away.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="pref-logs">
			<title>Logs</title>
			<para>
				<application>Gabber</application> can keep a complete log of incoming and outgoing messages
				for future retrieval. Most users will want to enable this feature for future use. To save
				disk space, logs may be purged once a month. It is advisable to save the logs in XHTML format
				for viewing in a web browser.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
<!-- END: PREF -->
