<!-- BEGIN: USERS -->
	<chapter id="users">
		<title>Managing Users</title>
		<para>
			Since the <link linkend="main-roster">roster</link> is the central point of
			<application>Gabber</application>, several functions are provided for managing
			the users and groups that make up the roster.
		</para>
		<sect1 id="users-subscription">
			<title>Subscriptions</title>
			<para>
				A subscription request must be sent and approved by a user before being able to see
				their status. When <link linkend="users-adduser">adding
				a user</link>, Gabber automatically sends a subscription request to the user being added.
				To manually send a subscription request (useful for when a friend accidentally denied
				a request), select <guimenuitem>Resubscribe</guimenuitem>
				from the <guimenu>User Context Menu</guimenu> (see <xref linkend="main-roster-menu"/>).
			</para>
			<para>
				On the receiving end of a subscription request, Gabber displays the <interface>Subscription
				Request</interface> dialog.
				This dialog also allows the user to add the sender to the roster and to rename the nickname used
				for the user (to be displayed throughout <application>Gabber</application>).
				After changing the customizable information, simply approve or deny the
				request by clicking <guibutton>Yes</guibutton> or <guibutton>No</guibutton>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="users-adduser">
			<title>Adding Users</title>
			<para>
				To add a user, load the <interface>Add User</interface> druid by selecting <guimenuitem>Add
				Contact...</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>Services</guimenu> menu or the first icon on the <link
				linkend="main-toolbar">toolbar</link>. The <interface>Add User</interface> druid will step through the entire process of adding
				a new user. If the new user's address is not known, the druid allows for searching through several Jabber
				user databases to find the user. Directions are provided through every step of the process. 
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="users-edituser">
			<title>Editing Existing Users</title>
			<para>
				The <link linkend="users-edituser-info">Contact Information</link> dialog (loaded from <guimenu>User Context
				Menu</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>View Contact Info...</guimenuitem>), displays a dialog for editing the user's nickname and and viewing
				personal information, current status, client information, location, and other specifics.
			</para>
			<para>
				Group management is accessible via the <link linkend="users-edituser-groups">Edit Groups dialog</link> (available
				from <guimenu>User Context Menu</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Edit Groups...</guimenuitem>).
			</para>
			<sect2 id="users-edituser-info">
				<title>User Information</title>
				<para>
					To find out all of the little details about a person on the roster, the <interface>Contact Information</interface>
					dialog is where to do it. Everything from their presence and status to their email address to their birth date
					to their operating system is listed within the tabs of the <interface>Contact Information</interface> dialog.
				</para>
				<para>
					Above the tabs are two important fields that list the person's Jabber ID and their resource. Use the drop down
					box to fetch resource specific information such as presence, GnuPG signature and client information.
				</para>
				<para>
					The <interface>General Info</interface>, <interface>Personal Info</interface>, <interface>Location</interface>,
					<interface>Organization</interface> and <interface>About</interface> tabs
					provides current vCard information (full name, email address, address, web site, etc.) about a user. This information
					is submitted through the user's client. Gabber provides editing of vCard information from the <link
					linkend="userinfo">My Information</link> dialog. The value of the <guilabel>Nickname</guilabel> field is used for
					display in the <link linkend="main-roster">roster</link> and in <link linkend="msg">messages</link>. The
					nickname field is edit-able.
				</para>
				<para>
					In addition to vCard information, the <interface>General Info</interface> tab shows two valuable bits of
					information. Exact status (or "away") messages given by the user are listed in the <interface>Presence and Status</interface>
					text area. This status information is set in <application>Gabber</application> through the Status toolbar (see
					<xref linkend="main-status"/> for more information). Below is a small icon that provides
					information about the GnuPG signature of this user. Hovering over this icon will indicate if the user has signed
					their presence and is thus able to receive encrypted messages. If the person did sign their presence, clicking on
					this icon will provide information on the signature. See <xref linkend="msg-encrypt"/> for more information about
					signatures and encrypted messages. Another useful bit of information is found in the
					<interface>Subscription</interface> area where the current status of subscriptions with this user is displayed.
					<xref linkend="users-subscription"/> explains subscriptions in greater detail.
				</para>
				<para>
					The <interface>Client Info</interface> tab shows information queried from the user's client application.
					If no information is shown or if the fields are blank, the user's client does not support that type
					of query.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		
			<sect2 id="users-edituser-groups">
				<title>Edit Groups</title>
				<para>
					The context sensitive <interface>Edit Groups</interface> dialog allows users to be easily added and
					removed from groups. At the top of the dialog the user's nickname and JID is listed for reference.
					The left side of the dialog lists groups that the user currently belongs to. Using the central
					<guibutton>Add</guibutton> and <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> buttons, the user can be added and removed
					from the available groups on the right side of the dialog by selecting a group in one of the two lists
					and clicking the appropriate button. To add a new group, simply type the name
					in the Group text box and click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>	

		<sect1 id="users-send">
			<title>Send Contact(s)</title>
			<para>
				An extremely handy feature of <application>Gabber</application> is found in the
				<interface>Send Contact(s)</interface> dialog. This dialog allows contacts from the roster
				to be easily sent to other users.
			</para>
			<para>
				After loading the dialog from the <guimenu>User Context</guimenu> menu, drag users
				from the main roster to the list in the dialog. Then information about the user can be
				displayed or the contact can be removed from the list. When all of the desired contacts
				are added, click the <guibutton>Send</guibutton> button to send the list to the specified
				user. As a small warning, there will be no confirmation if the list is received or not.
			</para>
		</sect1>

<!--
		<sect1 id="users-ignore">
			<title>Ignore List</title>
			<para>
				<application>Gabber</application> can protect users from bothersome contacts by keeping
				a contact ignore list. Users put on the ignore list will be blocked from sending messages
				and seeing current status updates. To start building an ignore list, simply add users from
				the roster or by Jabber ID to the <interface>Ignore List</interface> accessible from the
				<guimenu>Services</guimenu> menu. For even tighter control, disable the <guilabel>
				Allow people not on my roster to contact me</guilabel> option.
			</para>
		</sect1>
-->		
		<sect1 id="users-deluser">
			<title>Deleting Users</title>
			<para>
				To delete a user from the roster, simply right click on the user and select
				<guimenuitem>Delete User</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>User Context Menu</guimenu>
				(see <xref linkend="main-roster-menu"/>).
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="users-history">
			<title>View History</title>
			<para>
				If set in the <link linkend="pref">Preferences</link>, <application>Gabber</application> will
				log conversations between users. If logs are set to be saved as XHTML, <guimenuitem>View History...</guimenuitem>
				on the <guimenu>User Context Menu</guimenu> will load the log into the default GNOME web browser.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		
	</chapter>
<!-- END: USERS -->
